Finding Aid for Tailyour Family Papers
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- Tailyour Estate (Post-1815)
  - Hunting Papers
    - Hunting Journal, 1820-1826
    - Hunting Journal, 1828-1834
    - Taylor, R., List of Hunting Dogs, 1824-1827 (Box 24)
    - Taylor, R. List of Hunting Dogs, Kirktonhill & Cumberland, 1826-1830
    - Taylor, R., List of Hunting Dogs, 1826-1830
- Tailyour Family (bulk post-1815)
  - Correspondence
    The correspondence of the Tailyour family after 1815 is diverse. Many are letters from friends to unnamed recipients. Others are family telegraphs, which contain brief information, including traveling details, etc. The war letters are written to and from a long line of Tailyour men, who served in the military.
    - Copp, R., 1 February 1885 and undated, 3 items
    - Fenn, J F, 17 December 1868, 1 item
    - Lear, Edward, 24 April 1885, 1 item
    - Poynar, L., 4 January 1864, 1 item
    - Ramsay, Robert, 19 March-17 June 1864, 2 items
    - Smith, William, 5 January 1868, 1 item
    - Tailyour Family telegraphs & newspaper clippings, undated, 5 items
    - Tailyour, Hercules, 29 March 1918, 1 item
    - Tailyour, K. H, 4 January 1921, 1 item
    - Tailyour, William & S. Scott Robinson, 3-27 August 1970, 1 item
    - Taylor, George, 13 August 1868, 1 item
    - Taylor, Simon, 22 May 1861-11 February 1864, 21 items
    - Taylor, Simon (to Georgie), 7 January 1864, 1 item
    - War Letters, 23 October 1819-7 October 1920, 26 items
    - Watson, Robert, undated, 1 item
    - Wood, Marian, 14 May-17 July 1959, 2 items
  - Letterbooks
    The five letterbooks contain correspondence predominantly written from Great Britain and mostly detail financial and businesss affairs.
    - Tailyour Letterbook, 1796-1802 (Volume 17)
    - Alexander Renny Tailyour Letterbook, 1815-1822 (Volume 18)
    - Alexander Renny Tailyour Letterbook, 1823-1833 (Volume 19)
    - Alexander Renny Tailyour Letterbook, 1833-1849 (Volume 20)
    - Thomas Renny Tailyour Letterbook, 1854-1858 (Volume 21)
  - Account Books
    The Tailyour Family Account Books consist of four volumes, primarily concerning the finances of Alexander Renny Tailyour in England and Scotland.
    - Alexander Renny Tailyour Account "Journal," 1796-1816 (Volume 22)
    - Alexander Renny Tailyour Account "Ledger," 1797-1816 (Volume 23)
    - Alexander Renny Tailyour Account "Ledger," 1816-1848 (Volume 24)
    - Tailyour Rent Book, 1825-1848 (Volume 25)
  - Military
    The Tailyour family had a long tradition of military service, beginning in the nineteenth century. The collection contains military commissions and promotional records of George Robert, George H. F., and Kenneth R. H. Tailyour; a number of World War I prisoner-of-war records from Germany, including the envelopes issued by the German government to the soldiers; and World War I ration books. Also included are Mrs. H. Tailyour's journals from 1914 to 1917, with notes on the letters she received, daily news reports (often in several quick sentences), stamps she collected (and their value), war news, and assorted newspaper clippings. Finally, two nineteenth-century military books pertain to naval signals and insignia patterns.
    - Military Commissions, 11 July 1864-29 January 1925, 6 items
    - Military and war paraphernalia, undated, 22 items
    - Prisoner-of-war records, WWI, 22 items
    - Ration Books, WWI, 13 items
    - Tailyour, Mrs. H. WWI Journal, August-September 1914, 1 item
    - Tailyour, Mrs. H. WWI Journal, October-December 1914, 1 item
    - Tailyour, Mrs. H. WWI Journal, 1914-1915, 1 item
    - Tailyour, Mrs. H. WWI Journal, 1915, 1 item
    - Tailyour, Mrs. H. WWI Journal, 1915-1916, 1 item (Box 25)
    - Tailyour, Mrs. H. WWI Journal, 1917, 1 item
    - Naval Code Signals, Simon Taylor, 1832, 1 item
    - Scrapbook with military insignia, late 1800s, 1 item
  - Genealogy and Probate
    The genealogical records include birth and baptismal records, marriage and death records, and legal documents. A large family pedigree shows a very detailed and complete sketch of the Tailyour family. The genealogical notes and descriptions vary from simple sketches to notes on family history.Most of the probate records concern John Tailyour and his estates. The majority of these focus on the years immediately following his death, although there are some receipts of interest earned on the estate for several decades after his death. The will of Mary Watson, a member of one of the Tailyour family branches, is also included.
    - Genealogy
      - Birth and Baptismal Records, 6 February 1851-15 October 1904, 7 items
      - Marriage Records, 11 May 1841-25 March 1971, 5 items
      - Death Records, 19 November 1921-17 May 1960, 3 items
      - Legal Records, 18 September 1924, 1 item
      - Genealogical Descriptions, undated, 10 items
      - Genealogical Descriptions, 11 August 1870-14 October 1964, 9 items
      - Genealogical Notes, undated, 13 items
      - Genealogical Tables, undated, 16 items
      - Family Pedigree, undated, 1 item; In separate tube.
    - Probate
      - Taylor, John, Balmanna Estate, November 1804-26 October 1815, 20 items
      - Taylor, John, Estate Interest Receipts, 30 April 1806-30 April 1816, 11 items
      - Taylor, John, 2 September 1816-1 March 1819, 7 items
      - Taylor, Robert, Estate Interest Receipts, 30 April 1817-14 December 1843, 29 items
      - Watson, Mary, Will, 8 March 1887, 1 item
  - Printed Materials
    The printed sources in the collection are somewhat random in scope. They include a book by Hardy Bertram McCall, Memoirs of My Ancestors, about the McCall family. It is largely a biographical and genealogical sketch of the family in the nineteenth century. Two items concern the Tailyour estates: one is a description of the estates, and the other is an early-20th-century notice for the sale of Kirktonhill that includes photographs and descriptions of the estate. A number of newspaper clippings relate to the family.
    - McCall, Hardy Bertram, Memoirs of My Ancestors, 1884, 1 item (Box 26)
    - Marykirk & Kirktonhill, Descriptions, 22 November 1901-11 May 1923, 2 items
    - Newspaper Clippings, 14 items
    - Miscellaneous, 12 items
  - Illustrations, Artwork, and Poetry
    Several hand-drawn illustrations from the nineteenth century include two sketches of sailing vessels; one is a royal insignia, and another is a hunting cabin in Scotland. Fourteen engravings of fashion portraits (primarily French fashion styles) are hand colored. Two silhouettes are dated 1830. The poetry consists of loose pages of poetry and George Taylor's book of poems. One book contains a detailed, hand-colored blueprint for a tower. Two sketch-books were created by Kenneth R. H. Tailyour in his younger years. The drawings include still-life and natural scenes, as well as hand-drawn comics and humorous sketches.
    - Fashion Engravings, circa 1815-1820, 14 items
    - Sailing Vessel Illustrations, circa 1820, 2 items
    - Taylor, George, Hunting Cabin Illustration, circa 1850, 1 item
    - Royal Sketches, undated, 1 item
    - Silhouettes by Edouart, 1830, 2 items
    - Poetry, undated, 7 items
    - Taylor, George, Book with poetry, undated, 1 item
    - Architectural Plans for a tower, undated, 1 item
    - Tailyour, KRH, Sketch Book, 25 December 1917, 1 item
    - Tailyour, KRH, Sketch Book, January 1920, 1 item
  - Photographs
    The photographs in this collection center mainly on the Tailyour family. Though a number of still-life pictures of street-scenes and animals are represented, most photographs are portraits of individuals. A number have been marked with identifications, but most remain unmarked, and in some cases the identity cannot be determined. Kenneth R. H. Tailyour and his immediate family are the subjects of most of the photographs. Kenneth Tailyour was the father of William Tailyour, who donated this collection to the Clements Library. The family photos are of Kenneth Tailyour's siblings, Joan, Ian Stewart, William Gordon, and Norman Hastings; his parents, George Robert and Ada Tailyour; and his grandfather, George H. F. Tailyour.
    - Buildings and Street Scenes, 8 items
    - Dogs, 2 items
    - Horses-Hunting & Sport, 7 items
    - Horses-Portraits, 18 items
    - Negatives, 7 items (Box 27)
    - Portraits
      - Cartwright, Pam & Tailyour, Toby, 1 item
      - McEwen, Robert, 1 item
      - Scrupster, Mary Margaret, 1 item
      - Tailyour, Ada Hutchenson, 2 items
      - Tailyour, George H. F., 36 items
      - Tailyour, Kenneth R. H., 18 items
      - Tailyour, Robert, 1 item
      - Tailyour Family (K. R. H. and Ian Stewart), 6 items
      - Taylor, George, 2 items
      - Taylor, Mary, 1 item
      - Taylor, Robert, 1 item
      - Unknown, 57 items
      - Unknown (Military), 21 items
      - Tailyour, George Robert, circa 1909, 1 item
      - Tailyour Family (George Robert, KRH, and Ian Stewart), circa 1909, 1 item
      - Tailyour Family (George Robert, George H. F., Ada, KRH, and Ian Stewart), circa 1909, 1 item
      - Tailyour Family (George Robert, George H. F. and K. R. H.), circa 1910, 1 item
      - Tailyour Family (Ada, K. R. H. and George Robert), circa 1910, 1 item
      - Tailyour Family (K. R. H., Ian Stewart and Joan), circa 1912, 2 items
      - Tailyour, Ian Stewart, circa 1913, 1 item
      - Tailyour, Norman Hastings, circa 1915, 3 items
      - Tailyour Family (KRH, Ian Stewart, Joan, William Gordon and Norman Hastings), circa 1915, 1 item
      - Tailyour Family (Ada, K. R. H. and Norman Hastings), circa 1916, 1 item
      - Tailyour Family (Ada, K. R. H., Ian Stewart and William Gordon), circa 1916, 4 items
      - Tailyour Family (Ada and Norman Hastings), circa 1916, 1 item
      - Tailyour Family (George H. F., Ada, Ian Stewart, William Gordon and Norman Hastings), circa 1918, 1 item
      - Tailyour Family (George H. F., K. R. H., Ian Stewart, William Gordon and Norman Hastings), circa 1918, 1 item
      - Tailyour Family (K. R. H. & Danise), circa 1940, 2 items
      - Tailyour Family (K. R. H., Danise, Hazel and Ian Stewart), circa 1965, 2 items
      - Miscellaneous Photographs, 5 items
      - Empty Envelopes, 3 items
  - Ephemera
    The ephemera include postage stamps, menus, recipes, and especially postcards. Some postcards depict royal events and daily life. Most of the postcards, however, relate to the family foxhunts in the mid-nineteenth century. Each postcard is an announcement of a foxhunt.
    - Food, Menus, Recipes, 6 items (Box 28)
    - Postcards-Assorted, 30 items
    - Postcards-Foxhunts, 8 November 1852-16 March 1869, 98 items
  - Realia
    The realia in the Tailyour Papers include Robert Taylor's quill pen, a mini dictionary, and a mathematical and counting table.
    - Two plastic sticks (Box 29)
    - Port wine tag
    - Carrying sack
    - Rivet, circa 1939
    - "Do Not Disturb" sign
    - Counting Aid
    - Mathematics table
    - Mini Dictionary, circa 1850
    - Rock with attached paper
    - Race Club Medallion, 1932
    - Two 25 cmes from France, 1924, 1926
    - Collar with bell
    - Mini wooden shoe
    - "Madeira" stamp
    - "W" and "P" stamp
    - Small powder horn
    - Large powder horn
    - Lead ball
    - Taylor, Robert, Quill pen (from Account Ledger, 1826) (Box 30)
  - Audiovisual Materials
    The audio-visual material includes two items. One is a compact disc recording of an interview of Clements Library Director, John Dann, by Todd Mundt for "The Todd Mundt Show" on National Public Radio. In the interview, Dann describes the acquisition of the Tailyour Papers. The other is a collection of photographs showing the Tailyour Papers as they were when they arrived at the Clements Library, and some photographs of the papers in the process of being sorted. Included within this set are a number of photographs of the reception held for the acquisition of the collection, which features John Dann, William Tailyour, the donor of the collection, Clements library curators and staff, as well as University of Michigan faculty.
    - Audio CD of John Dann on the Todd Mundt Show (Box 28)
    - Photos of collection when it arrived, and reception for William Tailyour
    - CD of Tailyour West Indies Photos
  - Miscellaneous
    Miscellanea include a catalogue of books from the early nineteenth century; Robert Taylor's commonplace book; an address book (probably early twentieth century); and James Tailyour's Style and Form Book (1771), including stories, poems, and writing samples; and Ada Tailyour's communion book, which contains written notations.
    - Catalogue of Robert Taylor's Books, 1817, 1 item
    - Robert Taylor's Commonplace Book, 1842-1843, 1 item
    - Miscellaneous Address Book, 1 item
    - Miscellaneous Communion Book, Ada Hutchenson Tailyour, 20 May 1896, 1 item
    - Miscellaneous, 14 items
    - James Tailyour's Style & Form Book, 1771 (Box 29)
    - Penny Black Stamps, Located in Accounts, Expense Accounts, 1841-1842 and Accounts, Expense Accounts, 1842-1843.
Biographical Sketches of Noted Individuals in the Collection:
Anderson, Alex
John and Alex Anderson were both prominent merchants in London during the late-eighteenth and early-nineteenth centuries. They were John Tailyour's regular business contacts during his early years in the American colonies, and when Tailyour was in Jamaica he acted as a factor for them. The Andersons had strong ties to the Oswald family, who were also quite important in the British mercantile trade. They were particularly concerned with the slave trade during this period, owing to their involvement in that market.
Anderson, John
Alex Anderson's brother, and business partner.
Arcedekne, Chaloner
Chaloner Arcedekne was a prominent Jamaican landholder in the late-eighteenth century. Much of his time was spent away from Jamaica; he hired Simon Taylor to act as an attorney and overseer of his plantations in his absence. As an attorney to Arcedekne (and other absentee landlords), Simon advanced his fortune, allowing him to purchase his own plantations. Simon later became one of the richest men on the island. John Tailyour used his connection with his cousin Simon to extend his business network to Arcedekne. For more information on Simon Taylor and Arcedekne's relationship, see Travel, Trade and Power in the Atlantic, 1765-1884, ed. Betty Wood, New York: Cambridge University Press, 2002.
Ballantine, Peter
Peter Ballantine was one of John Tailyour's closest business partners and friends. Soon after arriving in Kingston, Jamaica, Tailyour entered into a business partnership with Ballantine, creating the firm of McBean, Ballantine, and Taylor in 1784. The firm traded in general plantation goods, although soon after forming, they began also buying and selling slaves. In 1792, they reorganized and added James Fairlie, changing their name to Taylor, Ballantine, and Fairlie. Much of the impetus for forming this partnership came from Tailyour's wish to leave all of his colonial business affairs in several hands, rather than continuing to trade solely in his name when he re-settled in Britain. Although Tailyour sold his interest in the firm in 1796, he maintained his correspondence with Ballantine. Tailyour even named one of his sons after Ballantine.
Bowman, John
John Bowman was an educator in Yorkshire, England, in the late-eighteenth and early-nineteenth centuries. When John Tailyour asked his brother Robert to find a suitable school for his son James in 1792, Robert found John Bowman at the boarding school of Byers Green Hall, in northern England. Tailyour sent James and two of his other sons, John and Simon, to Byers Green Hall.
Brand, John
Brand's most notable relationship to John Tailyour came with his role as Tailyour's agent in the Napier lawsuit. Napier leased part of Tailyour's lands in Scotland, and when Tailyour claimed that he had not paid his rent, he sent Napier to prison, resulting in a lawsuit in 1800. Brand later lobbied, with Tailyour, for the construction of a bridge over the North Esk river.
Burnett, John
John Burnett (1764?--1810) was born in Aberdeen, and served as an advocate, advocate-depute, sheriff, judge and judge-admiral in Scotland during his career. He served as officer overseeing John Tailyour's lawsuit with Napier over unpaid rents. After the lawsuit, which Tailyour lost, Burnett solicited Tailyour for the Office of Clerk and Collector in 1803. The Burnett family had long-standing, strong connections to the Tailyour family.
See also, T. F. Henderson, "Burnett, John (1764?--1810)," rev. Eric Metcalfe, in Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, ed. H. C. G. Matthew and Brian Harrison (Oxford: OUP, 2004)
Burnett, Col. William
Father of John Burnett, Col. William was a procurator-at-law in Aberdeen, Scotland. He had known John Tailyour and his family a long time; he shared John's interest in hunting dogs.
Carnegie, Sir David
Sir David Carnegie was a son of Sir John Carnegie, who was a brother of Jean Carnegie Tailyour. Davis was John Tailyour's cousin. He was instrumental in obtaining a position for John's son James in the East India Company, through his friend Lord Sidmouth, who was registered as the official recommendation in James' cadet papers.
Dick, David
David Dick was one of John Tailyour's clerks in Jamaica during his residency there. After Tailyour left, Dick and John McCall helped to oversee Tailyour's accounts in the firm of Taylor, Ballantine, and Fairlie. Soon after, Dick and McCall entered into their own partnership, which combined with Tailyour's old firm for a one-eight share of all non-slave business. By 1800, Dick and McCall had begun feuding. McCall accused Dick of not consulting him in the formation of the firm Dick, Orr, and Clark, and of mishandling three thousand pounds of their partnership's capital. The two asked Simon Taylor to arbitrate the case, but Simon was not interested in the affair. Ultimately, John Tailyour sided with McCall, which produced a rift in his relationship with Dick. After Tailyour left Jamaica, Dick helped to oversee and settle the affairs of Polly Graham, Tailyour's Jamaican lover and mother of his colonial children.
Fairlie, James
Along with Peter Ballantine, James Fairlie was one of John Tailyour's central business partners. Tailyour met Fairlie in Jamaica sometime around 1787, and began working with him in a limited capacity. On January 1, 1792, Fairlie entered into a business partnership with Tailyour and Ballantine, forming the firm Taylor, Ballantine, and Fairlie. This was a reorganized partnership of the earlier firm McBean, Ballantine, and Taylor. In 1796, Tailyour sold his interest in the partnership, but stayed in close contact with Fairlie for the rest of his life. Fairlie often updated Tailyour on the status and well-being of his colonial family after Tailyour left Jamaica in 1792.
Foulerton, Catherine
John Tailyour's younger sister Catherine married John Foulerton, with whom she had several children. Catherine became quite impressed with James Taylor, John's Jamaican son, when he visited in the early 1790s. She helped to win him an interview with the East India Company, through her connection with Lady Campbell, wife of General Campbell in India.
Foulerton, John
John Foulerton married Catherine Tailyour, John Tailyour's younger sister. Later in life he appealed to his brother-in-law, John, to help save him from financial difficulty.
Hill, Dr. George
George Hill (1750--1819), son of Reverend John Hill, was born in St. Andrews, Scotland. He was trained in divinity, and was introduced to a number of notable figures while studying in Edinburgh, including David Hume and Henry Dundas. In 1772, he became a professor of Greek at St. Andrews, and professor of divinity at St. Mary's College sixteen years later. Not long after, he became that college's head. Hill became a notable scholar, particularly in the realm of theological education. He helped to oversee the education of Simon, John Tailyour's son, who studied at St. Mary's. He also educated Simon Taylor's nephew, Simon Richard Brissett.
For more information, see Donald P. McCallum, "Hill, George (1750--1819)," in Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, ed. H. C. G. Matthew and Brian Harrison (Oxford: OUP, 2004))
Low, John
John Low often acted as John Tailyour's legal counsel after his return to Scotland. He was an agent for the sale of the Garrock estate for Tailyour. He was also Tailyour's attorney for his lawsuit against David Gray, as well as for the suit against Alexander Jolly.
McCall, Archibald
John Tailyour's brother-in-law, Archibald McCall, was the son of George McCall. After his sister Mary wed Tailyour, Archibald began trading with the Taylor family. In 1803, he traveled to Kingston, and conducted a fair amount of business with Simon Taylor. This relationship appears to have dissolved around 1809, after which point he moved to London to distance himself from his Jamaican concerns. One year later he returned to Glasgow.
McCall, George
Father of James, John, Samuel, and Mary McCall (John Tailyour's wife), George McCall was a prosperous merchant in the Glasgow-Virginia tobacco trade. He hired Tailyour early in his life to act as a factor in Virginia, but the events of the American Revolution soon forced Tailyour's return to Glasgow. Tailyour maintained a strong business relationship with McCall after he departed for Jamaica, and upon returning to Scotland in 1792, he met and married George's daughter Mary. A dispute over Virginia tobacco debts after the American Revolution hurt McCall's finances dramatically, and he sought out alternative markets elsewhere, including Bengal, where he traveled in 1800. Soon afterward he attempted to settle his tobacco finances with Tailyour, after the Americans and British came to terms on tobacco debts. George McCall died in 1810.
McCall, James
Son of George McCall and brother to Mary McCall, James McCall maintained a regular correspondence with Tailyour throughout his life. He did quite well, early on, in his business affairs. He traveled to Limerick, Charleston, and eventually back to Glasgow during his career.
McCall, John
Son of George McCall, John held a more direct business relationship to John Tailyour than his sibling James. McCall traveled to Jamaica, prior to his sister's marriage to Tailyour, in order to get into business there. He worked under the patronage of John Tailyour and George McCall's connections in the Americas. Tailyour hired the younger McCall as a clerk in his firm. Soon afterward, Tailyour returned to Scotland, leaving McCall in charge of his finances, along with his other clerk, David Dick. The two formed a partnership, which then united in a one-eighth share of non-slave commerce with Tailyour's firm Taylor, Ballantine, and Fairlie. McCall later blamed Dick for misplacing three thousand pounds of the firm's money, and for creating a new firm, Dick, Orr and Clark, without informing him. The two asked Simon Taylor to arbitrate the dispute. He initially refused, but later sided with McCall.
John McCall's letters provide some of the most thorough accounts of John Tailyour's Caribbean family. Along with David Dick, he oversaw their well-being and often conveyed their needs to Tailyour.
McCall, Samuel, jun.
Brother of John, James, and Mary McCall, and son to George McCall. Samuel, like his brother James, traveled throughout the Empire for his business affairs. He later moved to London to manage the affairs of his late brother, John's, estate.
Miles, William
One of John Tailyour's business contacts, William Miles traded in Bristol, hoping to open up greater markets in London and the West Indies. Much of his correspondence with Tailyour concerned Miles' need for better contacts in London, with whom he might be able to secure patronage for his son Philip.
Oswald, George